ABDULLAH N MALIK | Curriculum Vitae

SUMMARY ___

I have a PhD in Pure Mathematics, and my research interests are in the domains of applied category theory, graph neural networks, machine learning, graph theory, quantum computing, mathematical foundations of physics and mathematical philosophy.

EDUCATION _____

FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY

Ph.D. in Pure Mathematics

Thesis: Simplicial Methods in Graph Machine Learning

QUAID-E-AZAM UNIVERSITY

M.Phil. in Pure Mathematics

Thesis: Operator Algebras and The Foundations of Quantum Mechanics

COMSATS INSTITUTE OF INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY

B.S. in Mathematics

Thesis: Engineering Deutsch-Jozsa Algorithm in Cavity QED via Bragg Regime

8/2018 - 5/2024

Tallahassee, FL CGPA: 3.63

2/2014 - 4/2016

Islamabad, Pakistan CGPA: 3.80

2/2008 - 2/2012

Islamabad, Pakistan

CGPA: 3.28

Publications _____

Foster, T. S., & Malik, A. N. Wiesfeler and Leman Go Global Locally (in preparation)

➤ Capucci, M.; Gavranović, B.; Malik, A.N.; Rios, F., & Weinberger, J. On a fibrational construction for optics, lenses, and Dialectica categories, arXiv:2403.16388, 2024

▶Behzad, M.; Adnan, N.; Malik, A.N..; Merchant, S.A. Technology-Embedded Hybrid Learning. Preprints 2018, 2018030229. https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints201803.0229.v2

>Xing, Y. H., Farooq, M. U., & Malik, A. N. Effects of Gender on the Performance of Microenterprises in Pakistan. The International Journal of Humanities & Social Studies, 5(11). 2017

>Malik. A.N., Kamran. T. Orthomodularity and the incompatibility of relativity Quantum Stud.: Math. Found. 4, 171–179 (2017). and quantum mechanics. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40509-016-0092-8

Malik, A.N. Non-isometric, involutive antiautomorphisms. arXiv:1603.08498, 2016

Experience _____

ADJUNCT FACULTY

Florida State University

> Calculus II

5/6/2024 - 8/2/2024

8/19/2020 - 5/3/2024

Tallahassee, FL

Tallahassee, FL

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

Florida State University Solo Instructor:

> Calculus III

> Calculus II

➤ Calculus I. Content Creator:

> Course notes for Pre-Calculus

>> Fall 2023, Spring 2024

>> Summer 2023

>> Fall 2022, Summer 2022

Grader:

- > Introduction to Advanced Mathematics
- > Discrete Mathematics
- > Ordinary Differential Equations

Lab Instructor:

IN-CHARGE

> Business Calculus

Graduate Student Mentor:

> Student: Ayotuntosomi Loye

>> Spring 2023

>> Fall 2022

>> Fall 2020

>> Spring 2022 & 2021; Summer 2021

>> Project: Simplicial Sets are Chu Spaces

8/21/2017 – 12/26/2017

Office of Hybrid Learning

COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Virtual Campus

➤ Conceptualized and implemented a proposal for a policy framework and educational model on 13 degree programs

➤ Piloted the transition of 2 courses from face-to-face to hybrid for 16,500 students, that shaved off 3% of total expenses

➤ Led a team of 15 Content Experts, 5 Instructional Designers, 3 Animation Creators, 2 Video Editors and 4 Web Developers, ensuring successful and smooth generation, processing, editing and deployment of academic content

> Responsible for organizing and coordinating faculty development programs

➤ Identified gaps in student ICT literacy and provided appropriate recommendations for improvement

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE 3/9/2013 - 8/22/2017

Department of Mathematics

COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Virual Campus

➤ Moderated the following math courses:

>> Analytical Number Theory, Measure Theory, Operations Research, Introduction to Hilbert Spaces, Functional Analysis, Business Mathematics, Partial Differential Equations, Mathematical Statistics, Business Mathematics and Statistics, Statistical Inference, Algebra, Real Analysis

> M.Sc. Math undergraduate projects supervised:

>> Theorem of Maria Pia Soler, Non-exhaustive Properties of Multiplicative Groups of Matrices, Axiom of Choice: Equivalents and Implications, Current trends in Quantum Logic, Summing the Divergent, Language of the Universe: The Mathematics of Thermodynamics, A Comparison of Set Theories, Physics by SU(2), Automorphisms of General Linear Group, An Overview of Intuitionistic Logic, Extensions of Real Numbers, Constructive Calculus

SUBEDITOR (INTERN) 10/15/2012 - 11/23/2012

Pakistan Council for Science and Technology

➤ Subeditor for PCST's journal Science, Technology and Development

> Verification of data in Directory of Productive Scientists of Pakistan 2012

➤ Organised opening ceremony for Science and Innovation Policy, Pakistan, 2012

SUBEDITOR 3/19/2011 - 9/30/2012

UTrade (Pvt.) Ltd.

Islamabad, Pakistan

Islamabad, Pakistan

Islamabad, Pakistan

Islamabad, Pakistan

➤ Led a team of 16 writers, providing topic guidance and content development for company's signature monthly trade magazine UTrade

> Wrote editorials and summaries for chief editor for 15 editions

> Finalized printing and distribution of magazine to readers all over Pakistan

TEACHING ASSISTANT 12/2009 - 5/2010

Department of Computer Science

COMSATS Institute of Information Technology

➤ Conducted lab coding sessions for Introduction to Programming using C++ for 30 students, 4 times a week

Honors & Awards __

DWIGHT B. GOODNER FELLOWSHIP

Florida State University

Received additional stipend for Fall 2022 for being outstanding TA. Certificate

Spring 2023

Islamabad, Pakistan

OUTSTANDING INSTRUCTOR AWARD

Fall 2022

Florida State University

Among the top instructors in the Math Department. Certificate

AMS TRAVEL GRANT Fall 2022

AMS Awarded AMS travel grant to meet MRC mentor Valeria de Paiva to continue working on project developed at the MRC 2022.

ACT MRC 2022 Summer 2022

AMS

Attended Mathematics Research Committee for Applied Category Theory. Worked under Valeria de Paiva's group on Dialectica Categories. Fully funded summer school.

ADELAIDE WILSON FELLOWSHIP

Fall 2018

Florida State University

Received a one-time monetary disbursement as an outstanding newly admitted graduate student.

FULBRIGHT FELLOWSHIP 2017 Cohort

Florida State University

Fully funded merit fellowship for PhD, lasting 5 years with stipend, and book and travel allowance. Certificate

MERIT SCHOLARSHIP Spring 2014

Quaid-e-Azam University

Tuition waiver for M.Phil.

PRIME MINISTER'S LAPTOP Fall 2014

Islamabad, Pakistan

Awarded a laptop from Pakistan's Prime Minister for M.Phil. as an honors graduate student. Certificate

Fall 2014, Spring 2014, Spring 2016

BEST TEACHER AWARD CIIT, Virtual Campus

Top-rated teacher in all of Math Department. Received honorarium for performance. Certificate

PAKISTAN ATOMIC ENERGY COMMISSION TALENT SCHOLARSHIP

2008 Cohort

4/15/2024

Islamabad, Pakistan

Merit scholarship. Funded all fees for bachelor's, and included stipend and book allowance.

TALKS

Abstracts, slides and/or notes for the talks are available on my webpage.

COLORING GRAPHS AND BEYOND

Haverford College Pennsylvania, PA

Colloquium Talk

FINDING CLIQUES WITHOUT FINDING CLIQUES 4/12/2024

FSU Math Honors Day Tallahassee, FL

Flash Talk

WEISFEILER AND LEHMAN USE SIMPLICIAL SETS: PSUEDOTOP VERTEX NEURAL NETWORKS 3/22/2024

49th ANYSRGMC Syracuse, NY

Graduate Student Conference

FINDING HIGHER STRUCTURES IN GRAPHS 4/14/2023

Florida State University Tallahassee, FL

Poster Presentation at Math Honors Day

AN INTRODUCTION TO BELL'S THEOREM 11/04/2022 LOV103, Florida State University Tallahassee, FL

Graduate Student Seminar Talk

INFINITE SIMPLICES: AN EXCURSION INTO SIMPLICIAL SETS 8/19/2022 Florida State University Tallahassee, FL Public talk at Research Sharing Luncheon at Honors, Scholars and Fellows Society A COMBINATORIAL APPROACH TO SIMPLICIAL SETS 8/11/2022 LOV103 Florida State University Tallahassee, FL Topology Seminar Talk AXIOMATIZATION OF DIFFERENTIAL COHOMOLOGY 8/21/2021 Florida State University Zoom Algebra Seminar Talk THE VARIATIONAL BICOMPLEX AND TAKENS' THEOREM 4/22/2020 Florida State University Zoom Candidacy Exam Talk HILBERT'S SIXTH PROBLEM AND TOPOS THEORY 3/12/2019 LOV201, Florida State University Tallahassee, FL Graduate Student Seminar Talk COEXISTENCE OF SEVERAL NON-HERMITIAN OBSERVABLES IN PT-SYMMETRIC OM 4/23/2018 **Delaware State University** Dover, DE Presentation for a class project ORTHOMODULARITY AND INCOMPATIBILITY OF RELATIVITY AND QUANTUM MECHANICS 3/27/2017 International Islamic University Islamabad, Pakistan 3rd National Conference on Mathematical Physics MATHEMATICS AND THE FORMALISM OF QUANTUM MECHANICS 12/03/2015 Quaid-e-Azam University Islamabad, Pakistan Pure Math Seminar Talk MATHEMATICS AND THE FORMALISM OF QUANTUM MECHANICS 8/12/2015 COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Virtual Campus Islamabad, Pakistan Math Seminar Talk **ALEXANDER GROTHENDIECK: THE MAN** 3/12/2015 COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Virtual Campus Islamabad, Pakistan General Seminar Talk 1, 2,... 8/24/2014 COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Virtual Campus Islamabad, Pakistan Math Seminar Talk FIXED POINT THEOREMS IN TOPOLOGY: APPLICATIONS 8/17/2014 COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Virtual Campus Islamabad, Pakistan Math Seminar Talk THE COUNTER-INTUITIVE APPLICATIONS OF HARMONIC SERIES 1/1/2014 COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Virtual Campus Islamabad, Pakistan Math Seminar Talk WHY INTUITIONISTIC LOGIC IS DE-CONSTRUCTIVE 11/22/2013 COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Virtual Campus Islamabad, Pakistan

Math Seminar Talk

ENGINEERING DEUTSCH-JOZSA ALGORITHM WITH FLYING ATOMS

International Conference and Workshop on Nanoscience and Technology 2012 Islamabad, Pakistan

Conference Talk

LIMITS AND RANDOMNESS OF REASON

COMSATS Institute of Information Technology

Undergraduate Seminar Talk

8/4/2012

8/17/2011

Islamabad, Pakistan

SELECTED CERTIFICATIONS.

AI IN FINANCIAL SERVICES

6/26/2024

Upstart Network WWW.UPSTART.COM

>Use, limitations, benefits and ethic of AI in Finance

Certificate (2024)

Tallahassee, FL

DATASCIENCE BOOTCAMP 5/1/2024 and 5/1/2023

Erdős Institute WWW.ERDOSINSTITUTE.ORG/

>Project: Tallahassee crimemap generation using pix2pix.
 >Project: Predict initial configuration of Conway's Game of Life
 Certificate (2023)
 MASTER TRAINER

MASTER TRAINER 5/1/2023
HEC Slamabad, Pakistan

Faculty development training Certificate

SKILLS

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES Experienced: Python, LaTeX Familiar: C++ | SQL

LIBRARIES pytorch | sklearn | dgl | sqlite3 | Pandas | networkx | pix2pix | numpy | multiprocessing ED-TECH LMS: Canvas | Blackboard Grading Tools: Gradescope | Crowdmark

SOFTWARE CorelDRAW | Microsoft Excel | Word and Powerpoint LANGUAGES Native: Urdu | Potohari | Punjabi Fluent: English

Service and outreach.

READING GROUP Spring 2023 – Spring 2024

Florida State University

Tallahassee, FL

Initiated and organized a weekly a reading group on Applied Category Theory by arranging speakers and talk titles

ADVISOR Fall 2022

Student Advisory Board Tallahassee, FL

Volunteered on a student advisory board for the Honors, Scholars and Fellows Society at Florida State University.

JUDGE February 1, 2019

Capital Regional Science and Engineering Fair

Volunteered as a judge for a statewide schools' Science Fair.

VOLUNTEER September 13, 2019

Research Sharing Luncheon Tallahassee, FL

Volunteered for logistics support for Research Sharing Luncheon, organized by Honors, Scholars and Fellows Society at FSU.

VOLUNTEER November 30, 2018

Pakistan Day

Tallahassee, FL

Volunteered as a waiter, serving Pakistani cuisine on Coffee Hour, part of a weekly event that celebrates one country's cuisine at Center for Global Education, FSU.

VOLUNTEER February 2, 2019 & February 1, 2020

Math Fun Day

Tallahassee, FL

Volunteered for a public outreach and education event by the Math Department.

GARDENING April 14, 2018

The Spring Gardens Philedelphia, PA

 $Potted\ plants\ in\ a\ community\ vegetable\ garden\ as\ part\ of\ Fulbright\ Enrichment\ Seminar\ series.$